Guide to the Rose Franken Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Rose Franken Papers,
1925-1982
Franken, Rose, 1895-1988.
ca. 1,250 items (49 boxes, 46 v., 200 sound recordings)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4078782
Biographical Note
American novelist and playwright.
Scope and Content
Correspondence and manuscripts including drafts, typescripts, and proofs of Franken's short stories, novels, plays, and radio, film, and television scripts beginning with her first novel, PATTERN, published in 1925, through her latest volume, You're Well Out of a Hospital, published in 1966. Many of the manuscripts relate to her most famous characters, Claudia and David, who have become part of the contemporary cultural fabric. The collection also contains 18 volumes of clippings, approximately 200 recordings, and 501 mimeographed scripts relating to the "Claudia" series. Among the major correspondents are Faith Baldwin, Paul U. Kellogg, and Eleanor Roosevelt.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 10 series:
Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
Series II: Arranged Correspondence
Series III: Manuscripts
Series IV: Interviews
Series V: Clippings
Series VI: Photographs
Series VII: Periodicals
Series VIII: Books
Series IX: Records and Films
Series X: Flatbox Series
Subjects
Baldwin, Faith, 1893-1978.; Kellogg, Paul Underwood, 1879-1958.; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962.; Literature publishing.; American literature--20th century.; Radio scripts.; Television scripts.; Motion picture plays.; Scripts.; Women authors, American.; Women dramatists, American.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Acquisition
1966 M-66 Franken, Rose Gift
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
  - Crawford, Joan
  - Fadiman, Clifton
  - Fontanne, Lynn
  - Hughes, Robert
  - Kellogg, Paul
  - Perkins, Maxwell E.
  - Rodgers, Richard
  - Roosevelt, Eleanor
  - Webster, Margaret
- Series II Arranged Correspondence
  - White House correspondence
  - Personal correspondence
  - Correspondence relating to "Claudia" and other plays
  - Fan mail
- Series III: Manuscripts
  - "Another Claudia", Farrar & Rinehart, 1943, (Original typescript, much amended; Carbon typescript, used as printer's copy, much amended) (Box 1)
  - "Another Language", Samuel French, 1932; 1941; [n.d.], (3 Published editions) (Box 1)
  - "The Antic Years", Doubleday, 1958, (Original carbon typescript, much amended) (Box 2)
  - "The Book of Claudia", Farrar & Rinehart, [n.d.], (Published edition) (Box 3)
  - "Claudia", (1 Typescript for Doubleday ed., amended, 2 Published editions (Farrar & Rinehart, 1941), 2 Copies (Doubleday, 1954)) (Box 3-5)
  - "Claudia, a comedy drama", (1 Original carbon typescript, amended, 2 Published editions (Farrar & Rinehart, 1941), 1 Copy (Samuel French, 1942)) (Box 6)
  - "Claudia, aand David", Farrar & Rinehart, 1940, (1 Published edition) (Box 6)
  - "Claudia, aand David", [n.p.], 13 February 1946, (1 Typescript for film version) (Box 6)
  - "Claudia, aand David", [n.p.], 20 February 1946, (1 Mineographed shooting script for film version) (Box 6)
  - Claudia Television Scripts: "Important Decisions", [n.p.], 27 October 1958, (1 Mineographed) (Box 6)
  - Claudia Television Scripts: "The Special Talent", [n.p.], 22 January 1962, (1 Mineographed) (Box 6)
  - Claudia Omnibus: a) The Book of Claudia; b) Another Claudia; c) Young Claudia; d) The Marriage of Claudia; e) The Antic Years; f) From Claudia to David, Doubleday, 1958, (Amended copies of the books) (Box 7)
  - "The Fragile Years", Doubleday, 1952, (1 Original typescript, much amended, 1 Galley proof, date 15 July 1952) (Box 8)
  - "From Claudia to David", (1 Original typescript, much amended, 1 Typed copy for printer, amended) (Box 9)
  - "Gold Pennies", Constable, 1933, (2 copies) (Box 9)
  - "The Hallams", Samuel French, 1948, (1 Mimeographed acting version, 1 Mimeographed acting version, much amended, 1 Mimeographed version) (Box 10)
  - "Intimate Story", Doubleday, 1955, (1 Original typescript, much amended, with title "Happy Dream", 1 Typed carbon, printer's copy, 1 Galley proofs) (Box 11 & 12)
  - "The Marriage of Claudia", Rinehart, 1948, (1 Carbon typescript, amended) (Box 12)
  - "Of Great Riches", Longmans, Green, 1937, (1 Published edition) (Box 13)
  - "Outrageous Fortune", Samuel French, 1944, (1 Typescript draft, with tile "Crystal", 1 Acting typescript, amended) (Box 13)
  - "Pattern", (1 Original typescript, amended) (Box 13)
  - "Rendezvous", Doubleday, 1954, (1 Original typescript, much amended, 1 Typed carbon for printer, amended, 1 Original galley proofs, corrected) (Box 14)
  - "Second Thoughts on the First Lady", Privately printed, 1943, (1 Original carbon typescript, amended) (Box 14)
  - "Soldier's Wife", Samuel French, 1945, (2 copies) (Box 15)
  - "Soldier's Wife", Samuel French, green paper, 1945, (1 Early draft, carbon, much amended, 2 Typescript, acting version) (Box 15)
  - "Twice Born", Scribner's, 1935, (1 Published edition) (Box 15)
  - "Twice Born", Scribner's, 1935 (Box 42)
    [Much amended in the text for the 1969 edition]
  - "When All is Said and Done" [autobiography], (1 Original typescript, much amended, 1 Carbon typescript, much amended, 1 Gallye proof, corrected) (Box 16-18)
  - "When Doctors Disagree", (1 Typescript (original and carbon mixed), much amended) (Box 19)
  - "The Wing; a comedy drama in two acts", (3 Typescripts, much amended, 2 Mimegraphed copies, much amended) (Box 19 &42)
  - "You're Well Out of a Hospital", Doubleday, 1966, (1 Original typescript, amended, 1 Galley proof, 1 Published edition) (Box 20)
  - "Young Claudia", Rinehart, 1946, (1 Original typescript, amended) (Box 19)
  - "Claudia", (501 Radio Scripts) (Box 21-39)
  - Miscellaneous Manuscripts, (16 Typescripts of stories, sketches, and plays) (Box 30)
  - Film Scripts, (37 Mimeographed scripts, several in typescript) (Box 27-29)
    [Written by Rose Franken in conjunctiopn with William brown Meloney]
- Series IV: Interviews
  - Kerr, David Interview of Rose Franken by her grandnephew, (3 Audio tapes, 1 Typescript transcript) (Box 41)
    [Gift of David Kerr, 1988]
- Series V: Clippings
  - Clippings (Box 40 & 41)
- Series VI: Photographs
  - Photographs (Box 41)
- Series VII: Periodicals
  - "Return of Claudia", Good Housekeeping, July 1950 (Box 43)
  - "The Strongest Cord of All; a Claudia Story", Redbook, June 1952, (2 Copies) (Box 43)
  - "Little Cakes", Harper's Bazaar, January 1938 (Box 43)
  - "Little Cakes", Sunday News, 1927 (Box 43)
  - "About Rose Franken", (6 Magazines, 1 Book) (Box 43)
- Series VIII: Books
  - Books by Rose Franken, (69 Volumes, 39 Duplicate volumes) (Box 44-49)
- Series IX: Records and Films
  In Cage #6
  - Claudia Record Album (Box 1)
  - 397-380... (Box 2)
  - Claudia Program #99, #100... (Box 3)
  - 197 & 198 (Box 4)
  - 353 & 354 (Box 5)
  - 189 & 190 (Box 6)
  - 231 & 232 (Box 7)
  - 345 & 346 (Box 8)
  - 301 & 302 (Box 9)
  - Cinemart (Box 10)
  - Bess Johnson Audition (Box 11)
  - Phondisc "The Wing" (Box 12)
  - Phondisc "Young Claudia" (Box 13)
  - "Claudia" Motion Picture (Box 14)
  - "Claudia" Motion Picture (Box 15)
- Series X: Flatbox Series
  - "What America Thinks of Claudia", (1 Scrapbook) (Box 66)
  - "The Soldier's Wife", (1 Scrapbook of clippings) (Box 66)
  - "Claudia", (1 Scrapbook of clippings) (Box 66)
  - Newspaper clippings and reviews, (1 Scrapbook of clippings) (Box 67)
  - Newspaper clippings, (1 Scrapbook of clippings) (Box 68)
  - "Daytime Radio and Increased Sales Volume", (1 Bound volume) (Box 68)
  - Newspapers clippings, (1 Scrapbook) (Box 69)
  - Promotional posters (Box 70)
  - Promotional posters; stage photos (Box 71)
  - Stage photos (Box 72)